JOE: Abuse is when an individual is hurt
or treated badly, it is always wrong
and should never happen, but often does.
It is never the fault of the
individual concerned it is
always the fault of the abuser.
It can happen once or many times and can
include different types of abuse and may
get more serious the more it happens.
BETH: Individuals with autism may
have problems protecting themselves
against harm, abuse or being taken
advantage of as they might not know
what abuse is, or what has happened
to them and how it could affect them.
They should be taught how to recognise
potential abuse and they should be able to
identify at least two trusted adults they
can report abuse to or go to for help.
JOE: An individual should always
be listened to and believed when
they report abuse, they should also
be told about their rights and be
supported when reporting abuse.
Anyone who works with or cares
for individuals with autism should
understand what abuse is, and work
to make sure it doesn’t happen.
BETH: Families can educate themselves
and their loved one, on how to identify
warning signs and how to report
if abuse or neglect is suspected.
They should talk openly to their
family member about personal safety,
boundaries, saying ‘no’, and what
is a healthy and unhealthy touch.
They may even try doing role
play to show what is a dangerous
situation and how to respond.
JOE: The problem is that as a child
with autism grows up, they are taught to
respond more positively to people and to
be more responsive in social interactions.
But when the potential is there for abuse,
it is harder for them to understand that
not all people are honest and trustworthy
and have their best interests at heart.
BETH: Individuals need to remember
that they do not have to do things
because others tell them to, and if
something feels wrong it probably is.
If an individual has the confidence
to assert themselves and stand up
to a potential abuser, knowing that
when they say ‘no’ it means ‘no’,
they are more likely to prevent
themselves from harm and abuse.